Guide to the Printmaker File [1730]-present, (bulk 1800-1860) PR 58
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Prints 16 x 20" and smaller
  - Wyllie, William L., 1851-1931
    - [Ship in New York Harbor, with tugboats], ca. 1895-1903
  - Zabriskie, George A., 1868-1954
    - Ten untitled prints, undated
- Series II: Prints 16 x 20" to 30 x 40"
  Series II. Prints 16 x 20" to 30 x 40," is also filed by artist or printmaker's surname. The prints are are housed in drawers in flat files. This series contains many important eighteenth-century prints, particularly views of New York City.
  Three of Karl Akrell's engravings after Axel Leonhard Klinckowstrom are from Klinckowstrom's Atlas, which was published in Sweden in 1824. A complete copy of this early work is also held by the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections. The view of City Hall is notable for the pigs shown prominently in the foreground.
  Pierre Charles Canot, a French engraver working in London, engraved these two views of New York City after drawings by Thomas Howdell, a member of the Royal Artillery of the British Army. They were published in London in around 1768 as part of Scenographia America, a collection of twenty-eight views of American cities. The view from the south-east includes one of the first impressions of King's College (now Columbia University).
  Amos Doolittle's son A. B. Doolittle's engraving of Yale College is included in this series.
  The French lithographing firm of Engelmann Pére et Fils (Godefroy Engelmann, principal) completed six scenes of Vues de L'Amerique du Nord; all six were printed as the basis for wallpaper blocks. Complete sets are rare; the Society has three. The view of New York includes African Americans.
  The etching by Paul Fourdrinier is the earliest plan of Savannah known to exist. The first settlers came in 1733, and the print was issued the next year.
  Ambroise-Louis Garneray, a French artist and engraver, issued a series of travel views in the early eighteenth century, Vues des coites de France dans l'Ocean et dans la Mediteranee. The fifth volume, Voyage Maritime, featured views of great port cities, including several American ports. Garneray never visited America but copied the views of other artists.
  Thomas Johnston's view of the battle at Lake George is from the French and Indian War.
  Paul Sandby 1725-1809 is considered the founder of the watercolor movement in England, and was also the first English artist to use the aquatint process. The views by and after Sandby here were originally sketches by the colonial Massachusetts Governor Thomas Pownall. Sandby painted each view, and engraved several of them. The six prints here were first published in 1761 under the title of Six Remarkable Views in the Provinces of New-York, New-Jersey, and Pennsylvania, in North America, and were later reissued as part of Scenographia Americana, mentioned above, in 1768.
  Prints are filed alphabetically by artist or printmaker's surname.
  - Akrell, Carl Frederik, 1779-1868, after Axel Leonhard Klinckowstrom, 1775-1837
    - "Broadway -Gatan Och Radhuset I New York" [Broadway and City Hall], 1819
    - "New Yorks Hamn Och Redd Fran Brooklyn Pa Long Island" [New York Harbor from Brooklyn], 1820
      aquatint, 2 copies
    - "Chancellor Livingston", [1819]
      plan of boat
    - "Atlas" title page, 1824
  - Brown, Goerge Loring, 1814-1889, finished by Alexander Hay Ritchie, 1822-1895
    - [New York City from across river], 1861
      published by George Ward Nichols, New York
  - Bry, Edith, 1898-1991
    - "Sold", undated
      lithograph, impression 9 of 20
      See also: Series I
  - Canot, Pierre-Charles, 1710-1777, after Thomas Howdell
    - "A South East View of the City of New York in North America", [1768]
      published by T. Jefferys, London
    - "A South West View of the City of New York in North America", [1768]
  - Cartwright, T., after a drawing by George Beck, ca. 1748-1812
    - "East View of Baltimore, Maryland", 1802
      colored aquatint, published by Atkins & Nightingale, London & Philadelphia
  - Dawes, D.B. (?)
    - [Village church], undated
  - Doolittle, Amos, 1754-1832
    - "A New Display of the United States", 1803
      printed and sold by Doolittle, New Haven
  - Doolittle, A. B.
    - "A View of the Buildings of Yale College at New Haven", 1807
      published by A. Doolittle & Son, New Haven
  - Edy, John William, fl. 1780-1820, after George Bulteel Fisher, 1764-after 1796
    - "View of St. Anthony's Nose, on the North River Province of New York", 1795
      aquatint, published by Edy, Westminster
  - Engelmann, Pére et Fils
    - "Vues de l'Amerique du Nord (1r au 10e le)" [Niagara/Vue de New-York/West Point], [1825-1830]
    - "Vues de l'Amerique du Nord (23me au 32me le)" [Jeux Indiens/Pont de Virginie/Les chutes de Niagara], [1825-1830]
  - Etwiller, ?
    - [Toll Bridge], 1926
  - Fourdrinier, Paul, fl. 1720-2760, after Peter Gordon
    - "A View of Savanah as it stood the 29th of March 1734"
      etching, two copies, both colored
  - Garneray, Ambroise-Louis, 1783-1857
    - "A View of New-York, taken from Veahawk", 1834
      aquatint by Sigismond Himely, 1801-1872, after a painting by Garneray, Published by Basset, Paris
    - "Vue du Port de Baltimore", [1843-1844]
      aquatint after his own design, published by Hocquart, Paris, and by Bailly, Ward & Co., New York
  - Graham, George, fl. 1786-1813, after Archibald Robertson, 1765-1835
    - "A View on Hudson River, taken from the farm of Mr. James Renwick upon Chambers Creek near Newburgh", 1795
      mezzotint stipple engraving, published by James Harrison, New York
  - Hall, John, 1739-1797, after Benjamin West, 1738-1820
    - "William Penn's Treaty with the Indians, when he founded the province of Pennsylvania in North America, 1681", 1775
      engraving, published by John Boydell, London, two copies, one colored
  - Hulett, James, d. 1771, after Nicholas Garrison
    - "A View of the House of Employment, Alms-House, Pennsylvania Hospital, & part of the City of Philadelphia", 1787
      engraving, published by J. Harris, New York, State II
  - Jefferys, Thomas, after George Heap
    - "An East Prospect of the City of Philadelphia taken by George Heap from the Jersey Shore", [1756]
      engraving, published by Jefferys, London
  - Johnston, Thomas, 1708-1767
    - "A Prospective Plan of the Battle Fought near Lake George on the 8th of Sept. 1755..."
      after S. Blodget
  - Jukes, Francis, 1745-1812, after Alexander Robertson, 1772-1841
    - "Hudsons River from Chambers Creek looking thro' the High Lands", 1802
      colored aquatint, published by Jukes, London, and Robertson, New York
    - "New York from Hobuck Ferry House New Jersey", 1800
    - "Mount Vernon in Virginia the Seat of the late Lieut. General George Washington Commander in Chief of the Armies of the United States", 1800
  - Pennell, Joseph, 1860-1926
    - "The Cut Toward Culebra", 1912
  - Podwal, Mark, 1945-
    - "Ship of State", 2002
      etching, impression 13 of 60
  - Rollinson, William, 1762-1842, after John Wood, 1775-?
    - "New York from Long Island", 1801
      aquatint, published by Wood and Rollinson, New York
  - Sandby, Paul, 1731-809, after sketches by Thomas Pownall
    - Title page, "Six Remarkable Views in the Provinces of New-York, New-Jersey, and Pennsylvania, in North America", 1761
      printed by Thomas Jefferys, London [includes list of 6 plates]
    - "A View in Hudson's River of the Entrance of What is called the Topan Sea", 1761
      painted by Sandby, engraved by Peter Benazech, published by Thomas Jefferys, London. Additional copy of a later issue, colored.
    - "A View of the Falls on the Passaick, or Second River, in the Province of New Jersey", 1761
      painted and engraved by Sandby, published by Thomas Jefferys, London. Additional copy of a later issue.
    - "A View in Hudson's River of Pakepsey & the Catts-Kill Mountain, from Sopos Island in Hudson's River", 1761
    - "A View of the Great Cohoes Falls on the Mohawk River", 1761
      painted by Sandby, engraved by William Elliot, published by Thomas Jefferys, London. Two additional copies of a later issue.
    - "A View of Bethlem, the Great Moravian Settlement in the Province of Pennsylvania", 1761
      painted and engraved by Sandby, published by Thomas Jefferys, London.
    - "A Design to Represent the Beginning and Completion of an American Settlement or Farm", 1761
      painted by Sandby, engraved by James Peake, published by Thomas Jefferys, London. Two copies, one additional copy of a later issue.
  - Seymour, Samuel, fl. 1797-1823, after William Birch, 1755-1834
    - "The City of New York in the State of New York North America", 1803
      engraving, published by William Birch, Pennsylvania. One copy of first state, colored, and one copy of third state [with added picnickers and William Morgan's imprint, ca. 1820], uncolored
  - Smillie, James, 1807-1885, after Thomas Cole, 1801-1848
    - "Voyage of Life, Childhood", undated
      proof with no publisher listed, printed by H. Peters
    - "Voyage of Life, Youth", undated
      printed by J. Dalton
    - "Voyage of Life, Manhood", undated
    - "Voyage of Life, Old Age", undated
  - Smith, Samuel, after Thomas Leitch, fl. 1771
    - "A View of Charles-Town, the Capitol of South Carolina", 1776
      published by Smith, London
  - Stadler, Joseph Constantine, fl. 1780-1812, after William Roberts, 1788-1867
    - "The Natural Bridge", 1808
      colored aquatint, published in London
  - Strickland, William, 1788-1854
    - "Monumental Church at Richmond", [1810]
      perspective and engraving by Strickland, aquatinted by William Kneass, published by William Kneass
    - "View of the Water Gap and Columbia Glassworks--River Delaware", [1815-1818]
      aquatint after Thomas Birch, 1779-1851. Two copies, one colored.
  - Tiebout, Cornelius, ca. 1777-ca. 1830
    - "A View of Rensselaerville Manufactory The Property of Mr. James Caldwell, of the City of Albany, Merchant, with a Distant Prospect of Hudsons River and the Seat of Stephen Van Rensselaer Esquire", 1792
    - "Loss of the Packet Ship Albion", undated
      after Thomas Birch, 1779-1851, printed by William H. Morgan, Philadelphia. Two copies.
    - "View in Noble Borough State of New York", undated
  - Varian, George, 1865-1923
    - [Jeremiah Vanderbilt House, Flatbush Ave.], [1911]
      Two copies, one a canceled plate
    - [Unidentified historic Brooklyn house], [1911]
  - Wallace, William H.
    - [Farmhouse], undated
    - [Man fishing], undated
    - [Man on horseback in forest], undated
    - [Rabbit by stream], undated
  - Wilson, James & Isaac Eddy
    - "Chronology Delineated to Illustrate the History of Monarchical Revolution", 1813
      published by Eddy, Vermont. Two copies, one colored, and another copy of the bottom half of the plate.
- Series III: Prints larger than 30 x 40"
  Series III. Prints larger than 30 x 40" includes prints stored in frames and in oversize drawers.
  William Burgis' "A South Prospect of Ye Flourishing City of New York" is widely considered to be the most important early view of New York. The print was originally printed in London on four sheets of paper and published in 1719-1721. In 1746, the plates were changed somewhat and the print reissued by Thomas Bakewell. A copy of each of the states is included in this series. Additionally, Burgis' 1722 view of Boston can be found here.
  - Burgis, William, fl. 1716-1731
    - "A South Prospect of Ye Flourishing City of New York in the Province of New York in America", ca. 1719-1721
      line engraving designed by Burgis, engraved by John Harris (fl. 1685-1739)
    - "A South Prospect of Ye Flourishing City of New York in the Province of New York in America", 1746
      line engraving designed by Burgis, engraved by John Harris (fl. 1685-1739), printed and sold by Thomas Bakewell, London. State II.
    - "A South Prospect of Ye Great Town of Boston in New England in America", 1722
      line engraving designed by Burgis, engraved by John Harris (fl. 1685-1739), printed and sold by William Price, Boston.
      See also: Series I.